Ich what's get started.
Looks like it's a Friday, so you can predict whether it's a Friday or not based on the attendance
over here.
We're going to cover a lot of exciting things today.
I mean, yesterday was exciting also, but we covered a lot of the basics of caching.
We're going to talk a little bit more about caching since it's such an important topic, and we're
going to talk about advanced caches.
And then we're going to switch to prefetching in the later part of this lecture.
Does that sound good?
And these are all techniques that are employed very commonly in existing processors.
Essentially everything you see in classes employed very commonly.
And some of the things that may not be yet employed commonly will be employed commonly.
So don't worry about that.
For example, the Seri bus processor that I keep kept showing the wafer scale chip.
I've been showing that for a long time, since they started and recently they IPO.
Then I think a lot of people at Cerebus are quite happy.
But this also shows that people are actually building these really, really different kind of chips
today that nobody ever really imagined would be commercial even 10 years ago, right?
I know that when Cerebus started, they had a lot of criticism, etcetera, but now a lot of them are
actually pretty happy and hopefully they will see different in the world that can enable us to do
different things in the world.
So it's good to actually think about how you can make the trade-offs.
Maybe you can be starting a company 10 years down the road that's actually changing the world,
right?
Or you could be doing research that's changing the world.
OK.
There are different ways of changing the world.
OK, We're going to talk about advanced caches.
This is an updated version of their readings slide.
We're going to see some more of this today.
We're going to start prefetching next week.
We're going to cover virtual memory and some more advanced topics.
We were talking about cache performance.
We did talk about cache performance.
We talked about improving cache performance.
We did talk about a bunch of techniques to do that.
There are many, many more techniques.
We're going to talk about some more techniques today.
We talked about software approaches.
Software is actually has a lot of say on how you can exploit the cache.
You can write code that's really terrible in terms of caching, or you can write the same code.
Well, not same code, but you can you can do the same computation with much better cache performance.
So it's good to understand how your machine is if you want to get the high performance right.
But today I'm going to talk a little bit more about missed latency and cost, which we discussed, and
how you can actually change your cache design parameters and algorithms to take this into account.
So we've already discussed some of this actually.
What is the missed latency or missed cost affected by?
Basically, how long does it take to fetch the data When you get a cache miss, it's affected by
multiple things.
One of the things is where does the miss get serviced from?
Where is the cache block?
And the second thing is, how much does the miss stall the processor, right?
If the latency of the miss is hidden, maybe you don't care about that miss as much.
And we talked about a lot of latency tolerance techniques like out of order execution, right?
Out of order execution was invented to tolerate long latency operations.
Now, if the cache miss latency to the next level is 10 cycles, you can tolerate it.
Maybe it becomes much harder if it's 607 hundred 1000 cycles.
So it's good to think about that some, some cache misses are less costly, some cache misses are more
costly.
But there's another another aspect to this.
How much does the miss stall the processor?
So I'll just go through these relatively quickly.
What level of the cache in the hierarchy can a miss get service from?
Whether it's a row hit versus row conflict.
Remember the DM hierarchy, whether it's a bank, rank or channel conflict, you can actually have
conflicts that actually lengthen the time it takes to service the miss.
So if you're unlucky, you could actually get delayed significantly in the memory system, right?
Queuing delays in the memory controller and the interconnect, whether you actually whether the cache
block that you're accessing is in local memory or remote memory.
We discussed that, right?
It could be in a remote server, for example.
It could be in the same rack, it could be in some other rack.
So it's good to consider these.
And there are many, many other things that affect the latency of the miss.
Where does the miss get service from?
There's also this aspect.
How much does the miss stall the processor?
Is it is it?
Is it's latency overlapped with other latencies like computation latency or other miss latencies?
Is the data immediately needed by the processor right.
This makes the difference between load miss and store miss.
Maybe you get a cache miss on a block that is needed only by stores, but then no load references it,
right?
That means that that is probably less important, but at some point a load may come and reference it
and then it becomes important, right?
So this is called the criticality or importance of the block.
It's good to consider that as well, right?
Remember we talked about critical.
Word first in yesterday's lecture, some words are more critical because you need that immediately.
So it's good to have an understanding of what accesses that you're making, what that the misses that
you're trying to service.
What is the different levels of criticality among them?
Is the incoming block going to evict a longer to refetch block?
That's also good to think about, right?
OK, so these are some things that affect miss latency and cost.
One thing that affects miss latency and cost is memory level parallelism.
This is a broad concept of the notion or concept of generating and servicing multiple memory axis in
parallel, right?
So if you look at this picture over here, the processor generates a cache miss because it gets to a
load.
And if it's an isolated miss, right, it waits for that miss because it's window gets stalled because
it it doesn't have a very large out of order reorder buffer, right?
OK, so it waits for that miss, but the processor may also generate 2 cache misses concurrently.
And if you think about these, even though there are two cache misses over here, the processor waits
for the length of 1 miss.
Assuming this, they're the same length, right?
Meaning that most of the latency of B&C are overlapped over here.
And if you think about this, these are a little bit less costly misses.
Another way of thinking about this is if I were to eliminate, if I were to cache one of these three
blocks, only ABC, which one should I cache?
What do you guys think?
Which which miss would you eliminate?
Which of these three oranges would you eliminate?
Yes, A.
There you go.
Exactly.
Yeah.
If you eliminate A, you basically reduce that timeline because you don't need to wait for that.
If you eliminate B, unfortunately you're going to wait for C, and if you eliminate C, you're going
to wait for B, vice versa, right?
So this is the cost of a miss.
Basically, A is an isolated miss.
B&C are parallel misses, and there are many techniques that are proposed to improve MLP.
Out of order execution was one of them.
Actually, one of the biggest benefits of out of order execution is memory level parallelism.
It generates, it gets to the next cache miss earlier than you would otherwise, Right?
OK.
And MLP actually varies.
We're going to see another technique called run ahead execution in the prefetching lecture that I
worked a lot on during my PhD.
So it's very close to my heart.
But basically, MLP in the system varies.
Some misses are isolated and some misses are parallel.
How does this affect cache replace?
I did something over here, but it came back.
It's not that.
OK.
OK, So if you look at traditional cache replacement policies, they don't take into account their
miscount or cost of a miss.
Implicit assumption is that reducing miscount reduces memory related stall time, but if you actually
have misses with varying cost or varying memory level parallelism, it breaks this assumption.
Eliminating an isolated miss, as you have observed helps performance more than eliminating a
parallel miss.
Similarly, eliminating a higher latency miss could help performance more than eliminating a lower
latency miss.
Then the idea is basically, let's take this into account in the caching mechanisms.
I'm not going to give you the exact ways of doing that.
You're, you're, you should read the papers for doing that.
But I'm going to give you something that we did like 20 years ago, more than 20 years ago actually,
that demonstrates that this is true in real workloads as well as in this simple example.
So if you look at the simple example, let's assume that you have a loop and you keep executing this
loop and you're accessing blocks P4P3P2P1 and then P1P2P3P4.
And the accesses to these are parallel because of the way you structured the code, etcetera.
And then you access maybe S1S2S3.
These blocks and the the access to those are serial.
And let's assume that or isolated.
Let's assume that you have only four cache blocks.
You can cache in the same set.
They all have to the same set.
We're going to look at how 2 replacement algorithms perform.
One is minimising the miscount that's Beledy's optimal that people considered for a very long time
to be optimal under some conditions of course.
And then another policy that is more MLP aware as we called or basically reduces isolated misses.
So let's take a look at how this works.
So if you actually have Beledy's optimal, you in the steady state, you will get all hits over here
you can convince yourself and what bellies optimal would do.
This is the state of the cache at this point in time.
When you get to S1, Bellies optimal will policy would replace the cache block that's going to be
referenced furthest into the future, which is really P1, right?
And I that's what I did.
I got a miss over here, but I replaced P1 with S1.
Beldi's optimal When you get, when you get the miss S2, it will replace the cache block that would
be referenced furthest into the future, which is really S1 in this case if you look at that loop.
So S1 would be replaced with S2, and similarly S2 would be replaced with S3.
And when you get back to the original loop, you'll get three hits over here and one miss, and you
will replace S3 with P1.
OK, that's the steady state.
So that's where all these optimal.
I kind of simulated it relatively quickly, but if you look over here, you get 4 misses, right?
Four cache misses.
The processor has four stalls.
It stalls for this miss once.
It doesn't stall for this.
Unfortunately, this is not very well aligned.
This miss corresponds this stall.
This miss correspond this stall, and this miss corresponds this stall.
So it stalls for four misses, three of these S1S2S3 and also ones for P1, right?
So this sounds good.
And if you optimise your cache replacement policy, regardless of the cost of a miss, this is the
best you can do actually, assuming against under some conditions right now.
Let's take a look at how you could do better in terms of execution time, not necessarily number of
misses.
Maybe number of misses is not what we care about in the end.
And this is actually surprising.
I think it's good to demonstrate that if you increase the misses, you can improve performance,
right?
And we actually did that with simulation and also real system, but I'm not going to talk about that.
So basically if you do performance of a replacement or MLP of a replacement, you would design a
replacement policy that keeps S1S2S3 in the cache, right?
You have four blocks available in the cache.
Keep three of them in the cache and I don't really care what else I keep.
Actually you could do random and the rest 1.
So you would get basically hits on S1S2 S 3 and here you would keep replacing P4.
You'd get essentially a bunch of misses.
Something is wrong with the animation over here.
But anyway, basically the key idea is you would get misses on P3P2P1 over here and hits on P4 and
you would get misses.
Well, A1 miss on P1 over here and no, you would get misses on P2P3P4 over here and you would hit P1
because that's in the cache.
So if you look over here, we got 6 misses, 123456, but we have only two stalls because the misses
are really clustered in clusters of three.
And we saved a lot of cycles because we got rid of these isolated misses.
So I think this is the sort of creativity that I really like in computing design, computer
architecture.
You come out with an insight, say OK, I'm going to question this 60 year old assumption.
And the assumption was minimising misses actually improves performance all the time, or at least
doesn't reduce performance.
And you show based on what you know of how the system works that that is not true, right?
And that's the demonstration that that's not true.
Then the question becomes, OK, this is very interesting, how do I take advantage of it?
How do I build a mechanism that keeps S1S2 and S3 in the cache?
And the idea in this work is really to figure out, so there's some stability in whether misses are
serial or parallel.
And if you actually keep track of what happened in the past, you can relatively easily identify
which miss is going to be serial, which miss is going to be parallel into the future.
And based on that information, you can actually skew your replacement policy such that it keeps the
serial misses, right?
That's the idea over here.
But you cannot do that very easily, it turns out, because LRU is very strong.
Also there's some sort of LRU behaviour that happens.
So there are different access patterns.
So you need to take into account some other access patterns.
So in the end, you need to design A hybrid replacement policy.
One is MLP aware 1 is more LRU friendly.
And you put them together and you decide which set uses which policy because the access patterns to
different sets differ.
And that's the design aspect as you can see, right?
You come out with a new principle and then you implement the design.
And I like talking about this so because hopefully this is the way to design cache replacement
policies going into the future and people actually have incorporated some of these in designs.
OK, let me give you another example of parallelism in memory access.
So if you look at a memory hierarchy, it looks like this today.
Basically MC is the memory controller, LLC is last level cache in the baseline.
What you do is you serially access L1L2 last level cache and eventually figure out that the block
that you're.
Looking for is not on chip, right?
So the processor is stalled for a long time.
Let's say this is an example latency tolerance limit of reorder buffer over here.
If you're lucky, in many cases you're not that lucky.
But let's assume that that's the case over here.
So the idea is if you can, basically you wasted a lot of time querying on chip caches only to figure
out that you have to go off chip.
The question is, can you have a predictor that predicts whether you should go off chip with very
high accuracy and you start the main memory access earlier and overlap it with the querying of the
on chip cache hierarchy?
That's the idea over here.
Basically you design A predictor and predict whether a cache miss, whether a cache block that you're
accessing is on chip or not.
If it says off chip, you start accessing the memory hierarchy.
Well, the cache hierarchy at the same time you send a request to the memory controller saying, oh, I
think what I'm trying to access is going to go off chips, so start the main memory access for it so
that you can overlap the latency of that main memory access with cache hierarchy access.
And if I am actually right, then I've saved a lot of cycles, right?
That's the idea.
If I'm wrong, I did some main memory access for no reason.
I wasted an energy, so hopefully I'm not that wrong.
That's the idea.
Basically the key is really to design that predictor that can predict whether you should go off chip
or on chip.
So if you're right, you save a lot of cycles.
That's the idea over here, right?
Again, this is another insight that you come up with.
The insight is on chip cache.
Latency is on the critical path of blocks that miss in the on chip cache hierarchy.
So how can I get rid of that access latency to be on the critical path, right.
Yes.
We only care about speed and didn't we care about the energy consumption of our processor?
Yeah, we also just issued every single word.
Yeah, Yeah, not, not necessarily because issuing main memory requests also consumes bandwidth that
could be useful for other main memory requests that you are really issuing, right, That are not
that are really going to miss, right.
So if you cared only about speed, you wouldn't still do this.
And also there could be other cores that are accessing the off chip main memory.
They may need the bandwidth, right?
OK, so basically how do you design this predictor?
I will not talk about that, but this is a paper that's one of my recent PhD graduates.
I think he was my 25th PhD graduate, Rahul Behra.
He wrote as part of his thesis and it was the best paper award at Micro.
Similar things are implementing existing processes actually to predict this, because it's really
important to do so.
And he designed a perceptron based predictor.
So it's really a machine learning, very simple machine learning based predictor to predict this
relatively accurately.
You can read the paper if you're interested.
You can also work with the simulator if you're interested because all of this is open source and you
can actually download and do things.
So there's more room for improvement.
Actually there was so much room that we wrote another paper on that topic, which is actually making
things even better because things are actually even more complex when you go to, when you do
prefetching, which we will talk about.
And also when you at the same time you're trying to predict whether something is going to be off,
off chip or on chip.
So things are actually much more complicated when you consider the broader system.
OK.
So these are some examples of things that actually you can do that almost immediately impacts
hardware.
Impacting hardware is in general very difficult.
You know, impacting software is easy because anyone can easily adopt, but impacting hardware is
difficult.
But if you have good ideas, people can adopt these ideas relatively easily.
Also, well, relatively easily, meaning people who appreciate these ideas and they want performance
and energy efficiency adopt these ideas, right?
OK, so OK, I can talk a lot more about improving cash performance.
Unfortunately, we don't have a whole lot of time.
I'll refer you to some other lectures that take much longer.
For example, victim cache is an idea that's developed in this 1990 paper, which we're going to talk
about later on, actually by Norm Dupi.
And the idea is if you have a direct map cache, you cannot essentially put two things in the in the
same set because you have only one thing in a set.
The idea is to have a separate caching structure called victim cache.
Whatever is evicted because you get a conflict miss, you put it over there and you can more quickly
access that victim cache as opposed to going to the next level cache.
There's an idea that was implemented in many older processors.
It's still actually is implemented in some way in existing processors.
So it's so effective.
So it's, it's good to think about that, right?
Another way of thinking about this is this is a poor man's associativity method, right?
You're getting kind of an associativity with.
Help of another victim cache as opposed to making your cache set associated.
OK, So there are also more optimizations, which we're not going to talk about, but I will talk about
some issues in caching.
Multicore because it's really important.
Caching becomes even more important than multicore.
Memory becomes even more important.
Multicore because you have more things essentially trying to access caches and memory, right?
So I'll draw some pictures.
Again, the same things.
So a lot of these systems that we have are multicore systems.
You've seen these and you've seen this 3D cache, which is also interesting.
More things to come over there.
But basically cache efficiency and cache performance becomes even more important in multi core,
multi threaded system because memory bandwidth is at premium and cache space is a limited resource
across cores and threads, so you need to manage the cache even better.
Then the question becomes, what are the things that are different in a multi core system?
How do we design caches in a multi core system?
A lot of the efficiency methods that you apply in single core also apply in multi core.
But now you need to take into account something else that could be executing next to you, right?
So there are many decisions and questions over here, like should the caches be shared across cores,
across threads or should they be private?
We're going to talk about that.
We talked about that a little bit when we talked about instruction versus data partitioning.
Similar trade-offs will come into play.
Basically, whenever you do dynamic partitioning, it's better for utilisation, not good for quality
of service.
Whenever you do static partitioning, it's bad for utilisation but good for quality of service.
Essentially, as we will see, how do you maximise the performance of the entire system as opposed to
a single core?
How do you provide quality of service and predictable performance to different threads when you're
sharing the cache across different threads?
Well, the answer is yes, it's already aware actually.
How should space be allocated to threads in a shared cache if you're sharing?
Should we store data in compressed format in some caches?
I'm going to start with that actually, because that's so important.
And how do we do better?
You use prediction and management.
There's a lot of work that does that tries to do you reuse prediction, for example.
I will not talk about that.
We don't have time, but I will talk a little bit about compressed caches because there's an area
that we worked on and that other people have implemented.
I like this area a lot.
The difficulty is like you cannot design extremely complex compression algorithms in hardware
because you, your latency is very important, right?
Especially if you're closer to the core, right?
L2 cache, for example, L3 cache, L4, maybe you have a little bit more flexibility.
But as you will see, some folks at IBM implemented a lot of compression algorithms, including
versions of this, and they found out that even in large caches, the latency matters in terms of how
fast you can decompress a cache block, OK.
The idea is basically how do you store data in a compressed way?
And what are the compression algorithms that are hardware friendly, right?
You may have seen compression algorithms that are very good for compression ratios.
They don't necessarily work well like LZW compression, for example, Lampol zip compression, they
don't work well in hardware because they're extremely complex, OK.
So one of the observations that we have made along with other people is there are some interesting
data patterns in real applications that are very amenable to very easy compression algorithms that
you can build in hardware.
So zero values, for example, there are some works that show that 30% of what you store in memory is
all zeros, which is interesting, right?
If you initialise, I don't know, these studies need to be repeated again.
Actually these days I believe in machine learning workloads, a lot of things are zeros actually,
especially with sparse workloads, sparse graphs, etcetera.
So we have a lot of zeros in our systems.
So a lot of these memory, you have terabytes and terabytes, 30% is zeros.
Think about it that way.
OK, Some of them are repeated values because common initial values, adjacent pixels, etcetera, they
look like this.
Some of them are narrow values because the programmer has a large data type, but narrow values are
stored in it and the programmer has no idea about the dynamic range of the values.
They allocate a 32 bit integer, but you only use the last 8 bits, let's say, and some of them are
other patterns, pointers to the same memory region for example.
If you have a pointer list data structure, they may look like this for example.
So the realisation over here is that these data patterns exist and we did a lot of analysis on real
workloads at the time and we showed that more than 40% of cache lines belong to these patterns.
For example, you can repeat these studies with existing workloads.
This is we're talking about 2010 over here.
Now the realisation is that all of these example values have low dynamic range differences between
values are significantly smaller than the values themselves.
So I can design compression algorithms that are called base delta encoding.
Base plus delta you basically determine some.
Value.
Let's assume that that's the first value over there in the cache block.
Store it somewhere and encode everything else as deltas from that base value, right?
And if I do that, my compressed cache line is only 12 bytes as opposed to 32 bytes, right?
So I save 20 bytes from right away.
I don't even need to actually encode the first one, assuming it is the first one, right?
So I could do better.
OK, the good news is this is actually a very fast decompression.
So if I want to decompress this thing, I need to add the base to all of the deltas in parallel.
And this is actually something that we have seen.
It's a vector addition, right?
So you just need a vector unit that adds those things.
And that's not a multiplication, it's a vector addition.
So that sounds good.
It's simple hardware decompression.
Compression is also simple, but compression is usually not on the critical path unless it takes too
long and it's actually gets you a good compression ratios.
The analysis are in the paper.
So you get a lot of compression ratios over here.
The question is of course, can you do better?
This is base plus delta.
So one of the important realisation in this paper, it looks like this this if you have a single
base, this is uncompressible, right?
But if you realise that if you can use more bases, this is compressible assuming this green and red
repeats, right?
So more cache lines can be compressed this way.
Unclear how you actually find the two bases because you need something that scans the cache block
which may be OK to build.
So it could be higher overhead.
So basically what we developed in this work is the first base is the first element in the cache
line.
That's the base plus delta.
Second base is an impulse base of 0.
And if you actually do that, you cover, you get almost as close to as you would get if you find 2
best arbitrary bases.
That's the idea over here.
So this is called base delta immediate compression.
And this is the decompressor design that I was talking about.
If the base is the first one, you basically base delta edition vector edition over here, right?
If the base is 0, that's even easier, right?
OK, so I, I can go into more detail about this, but you can see that the performance essentially
this simple algorithm achieves the performance of the 2X the size of a cache.
So instead of adding, multiplying the size of your cache by cache by 2X, you could actually have a
compressed cache.
You need to change the cache a little bit, of course, to make sure this works.
So there's some complexity that you add and performance improves because you're reducing the MPKI,
which is misses per kilo instruction, right?
You're really reducing the MPKI significantly.
OK, If you're interested, the sort of ideas actually you can develop and research, and I'm proud
that we have actually developed a lot of these ideas that went into processors.
One of the processors that implement partly this idea, but they also implement some other
compression mechanisms is IBM processors.
IBM designs these big iron systems and they've recently written papers about this enterprise class
cache compression design that describes some of the compression algorithms that they use, including
Bayes delta impeded compression.
And they have huge caches and these are actually, these are very expensive machines.
I cannot quote for IBM, but more than $1,000,000 machines that are sold to banks so that you can do
basically transactional and database type of computations.
They actually designed these really, really carefully.
So IBM still designed these systems for a long time and they have huge caches, as I will show you
over here.
This is one of the more recent systems.
You can see that the L2 cache slices 32 megabytes and there are eight, eight of them at 256
megabytes, right?
There's a dual chip module and there are 12345678 of them.
So 8 * 256 is something that's like 2 terabytes, No2 gigabytes.
Is that correct?
OK, not terabytes yet.
That's a 2 gigabyte cache on this, I guess 16 chip system, right?
Or I don't know if it's 16 chip, it's something.
No, no, it's not 16 chip.
It's this is a dual chip module.
So it's an 8 chip system.
OK, OK.
And they have some connectivity over here.
They can actually form a virtual cache out of these cache slices.
So they have actually very interesting algorithms they can use.
It's it's physical cache slices, but they can actually make part of that L3L4 cache, etcetera.
And they use compression.
You can see that there's a compression unit over here to compress these caches because even then
they need more compressibility.
These are some of the biggest caches that you see in industry today, but you need to pay a lot for
it.
And you can see they have done this is from directly from IBM's papers and they've done some
studies.
So compared to an L2 cache megabytes, these are all mega.
32 MB L2 cache, a system with 30 MB L2 cache, 256 megabyte virtual L 3 and 2 gigabytes virtual L4.
That's the baseline performance is 1.
If you actually double the cache sizes, you'll get about 10% performance improvement, only 10% for a
lot of hardware area.
And they show in this paper that if you compress, you get a lot better.
Very similar to what we have shown.
Basically you get a lot better in the sense that you get to about 10% improvement but at much less
cost in the end.
So that's the idea.
Compression can buy you a better trade off compared to having larger caches.
And if you're interested, you can read these papers from IBM, OK.
There are other companies that do compression like Qualcomm, but we don't get into that because they
don't write papers as much.
Let's say, OK, it's, it's good to have industry writing papers because they actually take a lot of
ideas from academia and they don't necessarily write about it.
Sometimes they don't have time to write about it, but it's good when they write about things.
OK, let's talk about another trade off, which is private versus shared caches.
Should the cache belong to 1 core or should the cache be shared by multiple cores?
So if it's a private cache, a shared block across different cores can be in multiple caches, right?
This is going going to lead to the cache coherence problem that we will talk about.
So this is what private cache looks like.
This a shared cache looks like we're looking at L2 over here.
So this is actually a bigger concept as we have discussed, instead of dedicating a shared resource
instead, instead of dedicating a hardware resource to a hardware context, allow multiple contexts
to use it.
This is called resource sharing.
Basically, should we share the resources or should we make them private?
And there could be many, many resources over here.
Functional units for example.
If you do multi threading, fine grained multi threading, then functional units are shared.
If you don't do fine grained multi threading, then functional units are not shared, right?
That's one example.
Pipeline caches, buses, all of the things you can share or not share.
So the big benefit of shared resources is it improves utilisation and efficiency.
Meaning in the end it improves throughput for a given area, right?
When a resource is left idle by one thread, another thread can use it.
And there's also no need to replicate shared data, right?
So there are benefits to it.
It also reduces communication latency.
Data shared between multiple threads can be kept in the same cache, so they don't need to move
between caches, right?
So it's also good to think about.
We didn't talk about communication misses, but that becomes a big problem when you talk about
workloads.
Actually, if I go back over here, workloads like these guys evaluated, for example, there's a 28 way
SMP symmetric multiprocessor relational database workload.
So there's a lot of communication misses that they get as well in these real workloads.
OK.
And also this is compatible with the shared memory programming model.
You guys have done parallel programming, right?
Probably have used shared memory programming like loads and stores.
This is different from message passing programming model where different threads don't share memory
address space, right?
So this is very compatible.
Now this of course leads to disadvantages also when you share resources, this leads to contention
resources.
This is very fundamental.
That's true everywhere in human life.
Also, when the resource is not idle, another thread cannot use it, basically.
Or if space is occupied by one thread, another thread needs to reoccupy it, right?
So sometimes this reduces each thread's or some thread's performance, or the entire system's
performance, right?
You can get into very bad conflicting situations in the row buffer.
For example, if you're executing alone your row buffer, the row buffer in the DRAM is for you.
If you're executing together with some other threads, you could keep switching the roll buffer.
As a result, everybody's performance tanks and the entire system's performance tanks, right?
OK, thread performance can be much worse than when it's run a lot.
Sharing resources elimates performance isolation because now your performance is dependent on what
else is happening in the system, which means you don't really get consistent performance runs in
your system, right?
When you're running your application, you get performance X once because it's running with a nice
thread, let's say when you're running the same application with the same optimizations, your
performance reduces significantly because it's running with an aggressive thread that actually
needs a lot of cache, for example, right.
So basically thread performance depends on quite executing threads.
And this actually makes performance optimization very difficult.
Like as a as a software programmer or a compiler, you optimise your performance a lot, but your
performance is not being optimised because somebody else is hogging the resources, right?
You don't know how much cache space you're getting basically.
So basically on control, sharing the great quality of service, in the end, it's, it can cause
unfairness and starvation, right?
Basically, if you are sharing resources, you need to efficiently and fairly utilize shared
resources.
So we worked on this problem a lot.
And if you have shared caches, you have high effective capacity.
Dynamic, you know, dynamic partitioning of available cache space.
No fragmentation due to static parting that we discussed yesterday.
I think I already talked about that.
Easier to maintain coherence as cache block is in a single location.
But if you have shared caches, you have slower access because cache is not tightly coupled with one
core right now.
You have to actually have some interconnect between the cores and the shared cache.
If you have a private cache, you can tightly couple that cache to the core because that's the only
core that's going to access it, right?
And cores incurred conflict misses due to other cores accesses, right?
I think we would discuss that, but I'm going to give you an example of this.
And guaranteeing a minimum level of service or fairness to each core becomes harder because you need
to somehow guarantee some space, how much space and also bandwidth to the core, right?
So these are actually issues that you run into when you share resources.
So this is one example like this was actually this sort of issues were discussed a lot when multi
core processors were coming in 2000s.
We did a lot of work in main memory and some caches, but there were also other works in caches.
It's one of the nice papers that talks about how to do caching.
But you can see one example over here.
This is in let's say thread that likes a lot more cache space, blue thread.
And this is another thread, orange thread.
And when you actually run them together, the orange thread's performance gets significantly reduced
because blue thread gets most of the cache resources you can imagine.
For example, orange thread has a small working set that fits in L2 normally, and the blue thread is
a streaming thread that streams through memory like brings gigabytes of data and caching is maybe
not very useful for that thread.
And when they are run together, you destroy the cache space for the orange one, right?
OK, so the question is basically, how do you actually fix this problem?
I will not give you a lot of mechanisms today because this is actually something interesting to do,
but one of the mechanisms is partitioning the cache across the threads.
Then the question becomes, how do you partition the cache?
Is it hard partitioning?
Is it soft partitioning, Hard partitioning?
Maybe you decide how many ways should go to which threads and then say, OK ways 058 belongs to this
thread.
The remaining ways belong to this other thread.
How do you decide how many ways go to how many threads, which threads, etcetera?
So there are a lot of questions over here clearly.
So sharing improves resource utilisation.
Can we get the benefits of both is the key over here.
And the idea is to design shared resources such that they're efficiently utilised, controllable and
partitionable.
So I said you have no wasted resource and some quality of service mechanisms for threads.
And this is a teaser.
You can watch more or attend our Computer Architecture classes to learn more.
And we don't talk a lot about reuse prediction in computer architecture classes, so that's really
important.
OK, any questions?
This is more of a teaser.
I want to cover cash clearance in the remaining 7 minutes so that we can go into prefetching again.
I will not go into a lot of mechanisms, but you can see there could be a wealth of mechanisms that
people develop.
Like when we were doing this research again 20 plus years ago, multi core processors were coming to
Earth, let's say at that time.
And initially there was little, there was a lot of resource sharing, little resource partitioning.
And we showed with a lot of work that you need to partition the resources carefully.
And now a lot of multi core processors have partitioning mechanisms, cache partitioning mechanisms,
memory bandwidth partitioning mechanisms such that one thread doesn't hog the performance of other
threads.
In fact, one of the first papers that we wrote on this topic was Memory performance attacks.
It was published at USENIX Security, where we demonstrate on real systems that one thread can
destroy the performance of another, and if someone is not nice, they could use it as an attack to
some other threads.
Yeah, OK, let's talk about cache coherence, because it's also fundamental.
And this is again shared.
Based on the shared memory model, threads and parallel programs communicate through shared memory.
For example, thread 0 writes to an address, followed by thread one reads from that address.
This implies that there's some communication between the two, right?
There's one example, right?
And hopefully, well, each read should receive the last value, the value last written by any
processor, right?
Now, this requires some synchronisation between threads that we're not going to talk about.
But the problem is, what if the value is cached in either processor, right?
How do you ensure that everybody gets the right value when they need it right?
So that's the problem of cache coherence.
Basically, if multiple processors cache the same block, how do they ensure they all see a consistent
state?
So this is one example, P1P2 here is our cache block, shared cache block X.
The value is 1000.
Processor 2 loads it into its cache, it's 1000.
Processor one also loads it.
They're executing different.
Programs so they can do that while different threads.
Processor 1 updates the value to 2000 OK and the value is now stale in processor 2's cache as well
as memory, right?
And when the processor to reads it, it should not read 1000.
It should get the most up to date value which is 2000.
It exists somewhere in the system.
The question is how do you actually get that value right?
That's the problem of cache coherence.
Basically a single main memory location should be always kept coherent across different threads that
read or write to that memory location.
So hardware cache coherence.
So you could try to do this purely in software without any hardware support, then you would go
crazy.
Either you go crazy or you basically destroy your performance, which is either.
I think both of them are crazy in the end, right?
You have this very capable processor.
You try to solve this problem purely in software without any hardware support, then your performance
gets destroyed.
OK, so hardware cache coherence is a necessity.
Basically that's why shared memory processors have hardware cache coherence.
Or they need a different programming model, which is also fine, like message passing.
But the basic idea over here is a processor or cache.
This is a particular form of cache coherence called broadcast based coherence.
A processor, a cache, broadcasts its rights, or update to a cache block to all other processors,
right?
And another processor, a cache that has the block either invalidates what it has because it's stale
now, or updates its local copy of the block, assuming the other processor broadcasts the data,
right?
That's the idea.
So this works nicely if the processors and caches are connected with a bus.
For example, whenever 1 processor writes to a cache block, it broadcasts the address saying I'm
writing invalidate all of the copies in the system, right?
Because I have the most up to All caches Snoop, observe each other's write and read operations.
If a processor writes to a block, all others invalidate the block.
So from a cache blocks perspective, assuming some things like write through, no write, allocate
local processor performs, processor read, processor write actions and actions that are broadcast on
the bus are bus read, bus write.
This is what your state machine would look like.
For example, if the processor has the block valid and it does a processor read, it doesn't send
anything.
But if it does a processor right, it sends a bus ride signal saying that, oh, I'm updating the block
and it basically stays in the valid state.
This is this is probably the more interesting part over here.
If you have if, if you have the block in valid state in the cache and if you receive a bus ride
signal, meaning somebody is writing to this block, you go to the in valid state, right?
That's the idea.
OK, So people have also developed other cache coherence methods as opposed to having like these
snoopy buses, you can have directories, and the idea here is to have a central directory that keeps
track of which caches contained every possible cache block.
So I can immediately say this is a bit more costly and it is a bit more costly.
Every cache consults this directory to ensure data is kept kept coherent.
For example, there's a directory near main memory, the memory controller that keeps track of which
cache has this block X, right?
It's essentially a bit vector.
And you have, you have the number of bits you have is equal the number of processors.
And if a cache has the block, the bit vectors, the the bit location for that processor is set to
one, right?
So now you can keep track of which processor has has which block cached.
And if someone wants to write to that block, this is per block, this memory controller needs to
sends invalidate requests to all of the processors whose bits are set for that block.
That's the idea.
I just gave you the basic idea of this.
Of course, there are many corner cases that you need to be careful about.
You know, basically this is the mechanism.
I'll go through this relatively quickly, But for each cache block, you have P + 1 bits in the
directory, one bit for each cache, indicating whether the block is in the cache.
And there's also optimization that you can do, like exclusive.
It meaning indicates that a cache has the only copy of the block and can update it without notifying
others.
Because it's really important, you know, if you cache the block and every time you have to go to
this directory to get permission to update the block, that's very expensive.
But if you actually, if the directory knows and if it has given you permission to update the block
without notifying anyone, then you can improve performance significantly.
That's why there's AP plus one bit over here and.
I read you need to set the caches bit in the directory entry for the block and arrange the supply of
the block into the cache.
That's important.
That depends on the interconnect also.
So essentially, if you think about this, the directory is really orchestrating the data movement
across the caches, right?
And on the right, the directory needs to invalidate the block in all caches that have the block and
reset their bits in the directory entry.
OK, OK, I think we've already talked about this.
So we have lectures on cache coherence and more advanced topics, but I'm not going to cover them
today.
Sounds interesting.
The more interesting thing is how do these all fit together, right?
We talked about a lot of concepts and we're going to talk even more.
And when you design a memory system, you need to take into account essentially all of them.
A real memory system, you need to take into account cache coherence requests.
You need to take into account all of the requests coming from different processors, accelerators.
You need to think about resource sharing, partitioning.
You need to think about prioritisation.
So there's a lot to think about.
You think about prefetching as we will see.
You need to think about how do you efficiently utilize things.
So it's not just performance, it's energy also, it's also quality of service.
I've introduced some of that over here.
Predictability, You need to satisfy the guarantees.
There are some, there are some threads that require guarantees, for example, when you're refreshing
the screen over here, when you're updating the screen, graphics units require some bandwidth
guarantees, right?
You need to ensure that those guarantees are satisfied so that users don't go crazy and don't don't
go buy some competitors product that does that better, right?
So a lot of action happens in the memory system in the end that doesn't get really discussed here,
but you should really think about these.
And it's really a place where a wealth of optimisations need to be done.
And in the end, I will argue next week that we need to rethink the whole thing.
OK, there are no burning questions.
Let's take a break.
Then we're going to switch to prefetching.
Let's be back when the bell ring.
OK, let's continue where we left off.
Now we're going to start prefetching a new, I shouldn't say even more exciting topic, but it's an
even more exciting topic for me.
And there's an area where we need a whole lot more improvement and there's more to do in this area.
Prefetching is essentially predicting what addresses are needed by the processor and bringing them
closer to the processor early, right?
And these are the readings.
Let's get started.
This is an area that I've been working on for almost 2526 years now.
And it's a fascinating area.
And there's still a whole lot more to do in this area.
And we have a lot more that we understand here.
And a lot of the ideas that we have developed went into real processors that billions of people are
using actually.
So in that sense, it's a very interesting area.
The downside is there's a lot more to do because memory is such a big bottleneck and we want to
prefetch the data early, more accurately, etcetera.
Next week if we talk about processing in memory, you will see that this will still be important, but
it will be it should be done in a more memory centric way as opposed to processor centric way that
we talk about today.
So the basic idea and prefetching is fetch the data before it's needed or prefetch the data before
it's needed by the program.
Why?
It's obvious.
Again, memory latency is high.
If you prefetch accurately and oily enough, we can reduce or eliminate that latency, right?
Sounds good.
And the big benefit of prefetching is it can eliminate compulsory cache misses, right?
Caching, as we discussed yesterday, was a reactive technique.
You can basically cache something only after you access it.
Whereas prefetching says I'm going to predict whatever I need, whatever the processor is going to
need or program is going to need.
So it's a very proactive technique.
As a result, you can get rid of cache misses that are classified as compulsory in the last lecture.
Of course, the question then becomes can it eliminate all cache misses, capacity, conflict,
coherence, And in the end the answer is yes.
If you do the prefetching well, it can eliminate all kinds of cache misses.
And in an ideal world, if you do prefetching really well, you would never stall for any memory
access because there would be some mechanism that would prefetch the data and bring it just before
you need it, right?
That sounds like a good ideal world.
It's very hard to approximate in real life, and clearly this involves predicting which address will
be needed in the future.
And this also works for instruction and data.
Instructions are a little bit easier because they're usually sequential and also in the front end of
the machine you have a lot of information with the branch prediction, for example, you can run your
front end much faster than your back end because in the back end of the machine where you're
executing, you're limited by memory access and the front end, you can keep running it such that you
keep generating predictions and you can guide the instruction fetch engine with the branch
prediction mechanisms that you have.
OK, so of course pre fetching works if programs have predictable mis address patterns or if you
design algorithms that can predict what your programs is accessing.
This is like two sides of the same coin, right?
What is the predictable MIS access pattern?
It depends on what is how you, how good your algorithms are in predicting something, right?
OK, in general, we're not very good at predicting randomness.
So if you have, if you're truly randomly accessing memory, then you're in big trouble basically
because there is no technique that works really well in that case.
Caching doesn't work, pre fetching doesn't work, or maybe I should say some different type of
prefetching will work and we're going to get into that.
That's going to be execution based prefetching.
You execute a piece of the program to prefetch for another part of the program that you're going to
run.
OK, so prefetching and correctness, a misprediction in prefetching doesn't affect correctness.
I'll give answers to these relatively quickly.
Because prefetched data, the mispredicted address is simply not used.
That's good.
There is no need for state recovery.
So in that sense, it's more relaxed than branch prediction, right?
If you mispredict the branch, you've executed some instructions you need to flush the pipeline.
Whereas in prefetching you don't have that problem or similar to value also.
And if you mispredict the value, you need to flush the pipeline right?
Now, of course, people have figured out more recently that prefetching can lead to side channels,
can lead to other security issues, covert channels.
ETC.
Those we're not going to talk about, right?
I think any kind of speculation mechanism is vulnerable to side channels, covert channels, and those
we're not going to handle in this course.
OK, So the basics of prefetching in modern systems, prefetching is usually done at the cache block
granularity.
It's a technique that can reduce both miss rate as well as miss latency, and it can be done by
essentially any part of the stack, hardware compiler, programmer or the system.
And I'm going to give you some especially hardware based prefetching algorithms.
But software has a lot to say in terms of prefetching also.
For example, at the system level, At the operating system level, people have developed algorithms to
predict when a user will start a particular application and prefetch the data of that application
from the disk to main memory based on that prediction, right?
Windows, for example, had these learning based algorithms that were developed in 2000s, etcetera to
do this reasonably accurately.
So it's possible to do it at the system level, right?
You're predicting what the user will do in that case, right?
And prefetch the data because loading an application is important from a user perspective.
If you prefetch that already in main memory, you can load the application much faster, right?
So this is a picture that I drew when I was a graduate student in 2004 or so.
We published in one of the articles.
But this is an example hardware prefetcher as it sits in the system at next to L2 cache you can have
today we have hardware prefetchers, like 10s of hardware prefetchers at different parts of the
system.
This also kind of shows you how dated things are because memory controller is on the other side of
the bus, it's off chip.
But that's not true.
Memory controller got eaten today by the CPU chip because we can put a lot of transistors on a
single chip right?
But this is one example over here.
A hardware prefetcher can monitor accesses that are coming to it.
It could be filtered by the 1st double caches and then based on what it monitors it can issue
requests to prefetch.
So it it sees a some access pattern and based on the access pattern is decides to issue a new
request thinking that the processor will touch those new addresses that it predicts.
So there are four, at least four questions in prefetching what, when, where and how, and some of
these are multiple aspects.
What is what addresses to prefetch?
Essentially these are address prediction algorithms.
When is when do you initiate A prefetch request?
This is really important because you could be too early, in which case your prefetch may need to
wait for a long time and it may even be evicted by someone else you need.
You may be too late.
Then the process is already has already needed the data, so you don't really cover the latency that
much.
Ideally we would like to be on time.
Where has multiple aspects.
Where do you place the prefetch data?
Do you put it in caches?
Do you put it in a separate buffer?
Where do you place the prefetcher itself?
Which love in the memory hierarchy and how is?
How does the prefetcher operate and who operates it?
Is it software?
Is it hardware?
Is it Co operative?
Is it some sort of hybrid?
Hybrid is the right answer.
Again, is it execution or thread based?
Like do you really execute code to prefetch data or instructions?
We're going to see different kinds.
Let's start with what what addresses to prefetch.
So you don't want to prefetch useless addresses that you're not going to touch later on, right?
Because prefetching useless data wastes resources, especially main memory bandwidth.
You don't want to waste it.
Also, as we have discussed earlier, generates requests that may use up resources that are needed by
some other threads, right?
If you're especially in a multi core environment, so memory bandwidth, cache or prefetch buffer
space, energy consumption, basically these could all be utilised by demand requests from the same
application or some other application or more accurate prefetch requests.
It's always good to think about that, right?
You're wasting resources if you're doing something useless.
So accurate prediction of addresses to prefetch is really important.
And prefetch accuracy is one of the metrics that we care about.
It's not the only metric.
And prefetch accuracy means what is the fraction of the prefetches that are used or needed by the
program divided by all the prefetches that are sent by the prefetcher, right?
So it's very simple.
Ideally you you would like to be at 100%, but we'll see that it's not going to be easy to get 100%
by giving up something else, some other metric that's also important.
So basically, how do we know what to prefetch?
And there are multiple ways of doing that.
You can predict based on past access patterns, which is going to be a lot of the hardware prefetches
that we will see.
Or you could use the compilers or programmers knowledge of data structures, or you could do some
execution of a thread, right?
So in the end, you design some sort of prefetching algorithm and that determines what to prefetch.
Let's have some fun with cache block addresses.
So we're going to do prefetching at cache block level, right?
And if the processor, if this is the access stream that's seen by the prefetcher, hopefully the next
addresses are easy to predict, right?
This is a streaming access pattern you have streaming is essentially you have a stride of one,
right?
And you can keep prefetching farther ahead this way.
You will be wrong only when the processor stops accessing the stream, right?
That's the idea.
OK, this is also easily predictable.
This is a stride of 42, as you can see.
Sounds good, right?
This looks a bit more complicated, but not that bad.
Is this easy to prefetch?
What do you think?
Yes, you get plus 2 + 3 + 4 + 2 + 3 + 4.
Repeating right here.
The deltas, multiple deltas are predictable.
It's 234234234.
So we need to look a little bit further.
And prefetchers like this that that can prefetch like these deltas are designed and they're actually
in the processors that you're using.
So this is called delta correlation prefetcher.
You're correlating deltas.
Whenever you see 234, you're predicting you'll get 234 again, right?
OK, now at least we don't have predictable deltas.
This looks a bit harder, but there are some things you can predict over here.
Maybe right?
XYTXYTXYT.
So whenever you see X, you can prefetch Y&T.
That sounds good.
Maybe there's something else, but I don't think there is.
OK, and there's another one over here.
Does this look predictable?
Yes.
How do you predict it?
Just for a set of options.
Exactly.
Yeah, exactly.
So base address is changing AZP and the offsets are always plus one 6 + 67 + 18 + 7 + 9 nine, right?
This is also predictable.
You just need to have enough bookkeeping to predict this, right?
And this could this sort of access pairing can happen to the data structures, right?
You have some data structure and then you have you're accessing some fields consistently in that
data structure.
OK, So you can see that there are a lot of predictable access patterns, and we're going to look at
some simple things to begin with.
Actually, a lot of prefetchers have been proposed for all of these access patterns in the end, and
different sorts of prefetchers are implemented in existing processors, hybrid of them.
Yeah.
So OK, when is another one?
When is a difficult one because prefetching too early leads to prefetch data that may not be used
before it's evicted from storage.
Too late might not hide the whole memory latency.
And ideally you want to be just in time, right?
This is really the timeliness metric.
This affects the timeliness of the prefetcher, and prefetcher can be made more timely by making it
more aggressive, meaning you try to stay far ahead of the processors demand access stream.
By looking further into the future, if you have a hardware prefetcher or if you have a software
prefetcher, you may move the prefetch instructions early in the code.
But whenever you try to make a prefetcher more timely by doing this, you lose accuracy, right?
That's the downside because if you actually are more aggressive and the processor stops accessing
that stream, you prefetch a lot more than you would have if you were less aggressive, right?
So that reduced your accuracy.
If you move the prefetch instructions earlier in the code, the likelihood that you will like the
processor will actually get to the code that you are prefetching for reducers because you need to
move it across branches and one of those branches may be taken and may take you through some other
path that which will make your prefetch useless, right?
OK, so that's the idea basically.
There's a clearly a tension between timeless and accuracy.
OK, let's talk about where Where has a lot of aspects which level of cache to prefetch into.
Do you prefetch from memory to L4L 3L2?
Do you prefetch directly from memory to L1?
Basically, where do you do it?
This is essentially insertion policy.
Where do you insert in terms of which level of cache do you prefetch from L3 to L2L2 to L1?
Do you have separate prefetchers for all of these?
There are many questions over here basically.
Or do you have a single prefetcher that prefetches into all of the caches?
You need to be careful in prefetching L into L1 because as we discussed, L1 is very special.
It's tightly integrated into the pipeline.
Size is small.
If you pollute it with a lot of prefetches, you may actually lose a lot of pipeline performance.
So in general, prefetchers to L1 are different from prefetches to other prefetchers to other parts
of the memory.
Do you put it in the memory controller?
Essentially, today prefetchers are everywhere.
Where do you place the prefetch data?
In the cache itself.
Do we treat prefetch blocks the same as demandfetch blocks even though they were not requested by
the load or store?
How do you decide how to treat them?
This is actually another interesting question.
Like in general, if you have some idea about the accuracy of the prefetcher, you may treat highly
accurate prefetches or predicted highly accurate prefetches similar to demand fetch blocks.
If your prefetcher is not very accurate based on the past, then you may treat them less like demand
fetch blocks.
You may, for example, insert the prefetch into a more least recently used position.
Right, OK.
Basically, prefetch blocks are not known to be needed with LRU policy that we discussed yesterday.
Least recently used, a demand block is normally placed into the MRU position.
The question is, do we skew the replacement policy such that it favours the demand fetch blocks?
Place all prefetches, for example, into the LRU position In a way that's a bad idea.
Turns out, because some prefetches are really accurate and you don't want to put them into the LRU
position such that they're evicted quickly.
You want to really bias them to be at a position where they will be less likely to be evicted.
So in general, using information about the accuracy of prefetches is very useful to decide where to
place the prefetches.
This is actually a smaller form of the reuse prediction that we discussed, right?
The idea is to predict whether a cache line is going to be used, and for that I think you need to
develop various mechanisms.
Prefetching accuracy is 1 one metric that could correlate with whether or not a cache line is going
to be reused, right?
A prefetch cache line OK Ware also has more here.
Where to place the hardware prefetcher in the memory hierarchy becomes important.
In other words, what access patterns does the prefetcher see?
Does it see L one hits and misses?
Which is right at the right before the L1.
Basically you put the prefetcher.
Does it see see L1 misses only or L2 misses, L3 misses.
So as you go farther away from the processor, the access stream that the prefetcher sees becomes
less complete.
In other words, filtered by whatever hits and the upper level caches.
This means that the prefetcher can act more slowly because it's not being bombarded by so many
requests coming from the processor.
But it may also be it may be harder to find patterns in those access patterns.
So seeing a more complete access pattern can lead to potentially better accuracy and coverage.
Not necessarily, but can.
But the downside is prefetcher needs to examine much many more requests because it's more bandwidth
intensive.
You may need to design A prefetcher with more ports into the prefetcher.
If the processor is able to issue 10 loads per cycle, for example, the prefetcher needs to keep up
with that right?
Ideally, again, OK, so recall there's a modern memory hierarchy and you could have prefetching
everywhere here, including into the register file from L1 caches.
Good to think about that.
OK.
And the main memory actually become is becoming bigger.
Things are becoming more hybrid in main memory.
There are different types of DM, for example, different types of memories.
And as we discussed, there's remote memory also.
So it's good to essentially prefetching is a really necessary technique to over overcome or overlap
the latencies or reduce the observed access latency to these very large memories.
OK, let's talk about how we talked about where how is and we talked about what earlier.
How is essentially?
What type of prefetching do you do?
And these are very broad methods, software prefetching, hardware prefetching, and execution based
prefetching, and all of them are employed in today's systems.
Software prefetching can be done by the programmer.
You don't necessarily need ISA instructions.
You can actually write your software such that a piece of your software prefetches for another piece
of your software.
That's very commonly employed.
Prefetching is a much more general technique, right?
But if you actually want the compiler to do some prefetching, your ISA may need some prefetch
instructions and programmer or compiler inserts these instructions to the code.
This usually works well for only regular access patterns.
It's very difficult to make this work for very irregular patterns.
If this was a longer lecture I would give you more examples, but we don't have time hardware
prefetching now.
We have specialised hardware that monitors memory accesses and basically uses some pattern
recognition methods, either memorisation or learning different types of learning.
I'm going to talk about reinforcement learning based prefetches later.
For example, finds these predictable patterns in the addresses.
It could be strides, it could be correlations, it could be these delta values for example and
generates prefetch addresses automatically, right?
This is nice because the programmer or the compiler doesn't need to do anything.
Of course, this may be this may work more easily if the memory allocation is nice and the access
patterns are nice.
If things are random, this doesn't work very well.
Basically doesn't work at all.
Essentially execution based prefetching is interesting because it could be hardware and software
either or Co operative.
Again, here you execute a thread to prefetch data for the main programme.
We call the speculative threads.
They're really not a thread to produce result, they're really a thread to aid the main programme
that produces the result.
They're also called helper threads or assist threads.
They really assist the main execution.
And you could as a programmer write this, you could actually think about doing that, or the compiler
can generate it or the hardware can generate it, right?
So essentially, there are many potential possibilities over here.
You can of course, have nice ISA support instructions that architecture support such that these
threads work nicely.
We're going to talk about that also.
So this is an example of prefetch instruction that exists in many IS as this is a version of X86 and
you can see that it says prefetch data into the caches and it's a mess and you will see why it's a
mess when I show you over here.
So basically you can look at the description fetches the line of data from memory that contains the
bytes specified within the source operand to a location in the cache hierarchy specified by a
locality hint.
Locality hint is a mess.
T0 if you supply T0 temporal data, prefetched data into all levels of the cache.
ARC Pentium 3 processor first or second level cache, Pentium 4, Intel's EON processor second level
cache.
Clearly all doesn't include the first level, which is interesting right?
Basically they don't want to pre fetch into LL1 cache because they don't trust the compiler or the
programmer.
You will see this a lot in speculative optimizations.
Whenever you enable the interface to provide some speculative mechanism, in this case a pre fetch
instruction, the micro architect decides how that is executed.
OK, and you can see that there is a bunch of hints over here, but they're essentially all the same
or mostly the same.
So the idea is non temporal data with respect to all cache levels, prefetched data into non temporal
cache structure and into a location close to the processor, minimising cache pollution.
So basically this is interesting because you prefetch into the first level cache but not into other
cache levels right?
This works if you have a non inclusive or exclusive cache hierarchy, right?
OK, anyways, there's more to be talked about over here, but software prefetching using these
instructions is done, but maybe the interface is not good enough.
This turns out it's not very easy to get very high performance with software prefetching.
There are also many, many other reasons like if you want to insert these instructions, you want to
figure out what's going to miss and you want to only insert these instructions for things that are
going to miss.
But the compiler doesn't have a very good idea of what's going to miss necessarily, right?
So it needs to do profiling, etcetera.
So this is a difficult task.
That's why a lot of processors use hardware prefetchers and hardware prefetchers are very common
today.
And this is one example.
It's a streaming prefetcher.
Basically, whenever you're fetching cache block N, you also you prefetch for n + 1 M plus 2M plus
three m + 4.
So you may have a distance, you may decide whenever the processor access address N, you bring three
more cache blocks, right?
And you keep the distance.
Basically, you could have a streaming prefetcher between L1 and L2.
You can see that you can have a streaming prefetcher between L2 and L3, and you can have a streaming
prefetcher between memory L3 and memory, for example.
If you're actually confident that you're streaming a lot, you may actually bring these next 4 lines,
4 cache blocks into L3, right?
So hopefully this idea is very simple, right?
Where basically increment the address cache block address and prefetch that from the next level.
And IBM Power systems employ versions of this prefetcher.
And this is their nice picture that I borrow from them.
This idea is relatively old.
It was actually proposed in this paper by Norm Dupi.
And this paper won the Test of Time award at ISCA a long time ago.
It was, it's from 1990.
They also introduced the victim caches over here that I briefly mentioned in the previous month.
Essentially the streaming prefetcher and a version of streaming prefetcher is really employed in
essentially all general purpose processors today.
But I like this paper for another reason because they talk about the increasing cost of cache
misses.
It's a paper that was written in 1990 and you can see the miss cost is 6 cycles in VAX, which is one
of the fastest processors in the 1980s from Digital Equipment Corporation.
And miss costs in terms of instructions is .6 instructions.
So this wax as 10 cycles per instruction as you can see which is quite high and WRL Western research
lab Titan prototype cycles per instruction.
Is 1.4 miss cost is essentially 12 cycles.
So miss cost is in terms of instructions, 8.6 instructions, right.
And this paper projects that miss cost will be 70 cycles and in terms of instructions it'll be 140.
Well, we're today well beyond 7500 is easily there.
And if you're finishing eight instructions per cycle 500 times it's 84000 instructions.
So costs have increased a lot as you can see.
OK, so let's talk about performance metrics.
We talked about accuracy, we talked about timeless.
But there is a very important metric which is coverage.
Accuracy is the number of used prefetches divided by the number of sent prefetches sent by the
prefetcher.
Ideally you would like to be 100% accurate.
Timeless is the number of on time prefetches divided by the number of prefetches that are sent by
the prefetches that are used for the prefetches that are used.
How timely were you?
Right.
This is of course timeless is not a binary metric necessarily.
Meaning whether used or not, you can think of timeless as a spectrum of the number of cycles you
saved, right?
So timeless can be also defined in terms of the fraction of the miss cycles that you have saved,
right?
So it's not just on time, it's like what fraction have you saved?
Coverage is number of prefetched misses.
Divide by all misses that you have in the programme, right?
So if your coverage is 0, your accuracy may be 100, but your prefetcher is useless because it's not
prefetching anything, right?
And if your accuracy, if your cover, your coverage may be 100, but your accuracy may be 0 and you
still degrade performance because you prefetch a lot of useless stuff, not close to 0,
approximately 0.
So you can see that these metrics can go against each other easily, right?
There's also other metrics.
Usually you can.
You can get two of these three metrics high.
It's very difficult to get all three metrics very high.
It's good to think about that.
But if you have multiple prefetchers, then one of them may be very good at accuracy, another may be
very good at coverage.
And also there are different access patterns.
Clearly a single prefetcher covering all possible access patterns is very difficult as we have
discussed with caching.
Also, there are also other metrics that we care about bandwidth consumption.
There's memory bandwidth consumed with the prefetcher divided by without the prefetcher, so this is
also important.
If you increase that significantly then you're probably wasting memory bandwidth, which is
important, but also you're increasing energy.
The good news is you can potentially ties idle bus bandwidth if it's available, so you can schedule
your prefetches in the idle cycles.
Cache pollution is another metric.
It's a bit more difficult to quantify, but it does affect performance.
This is the number of extra demand misses that you get due to prefetch placement in the cache.
We didn't talk about exactly where to place prefetches, but essentially all processors place
prefetch into the caches today because designing a separate buffer to place the prefetching
prefetches is a nightmare.
Memory system is already way too complex.
If you add another buffer just for prefetches, then you need to maintain coherence across that
prefetch buffer and your data buffers, right?
So essentially all prefetch, all prefetchers today prefetch data into the caches for that reason.
As a result, these prefetches may displace some of the demand requests, right and that causes cash
pollution.
So you can see that there are a lot of interesting things to optimise and in the end prefetcher
design is really optimising for all of these.
In a good trade off space, this is something that we're going to cover.
So in the end, prefetching can be actually very good for resource usage very similarly to what we
have discussed earlier.
This is data from Sun which was bought by Oracle later on.
And the idea over here is if you are effective in prefetching, you can improve performance and also
reduce hardware cost.
This is the run ahead prefetching.
I did my dissertation on run net execution and these guys were the first ones to really adopt the
idea in their processors.
This is on a commercial workload and the idea is no scout.
They called it Scout.
Their version overhead is Scout.
No scout is no prefetching.
Scout is with prefetching.
So you can see that regardless of the cache size you buy a lot of performance.
But if you look at a 512 KB L2 cache size, you get 40% better performance which is good.
If you look over here, you can have a one MB cache with scout prefetching which by which essentially
has the same performance of no prefetching, no scout prefetching with an 8 megabyte cache.
So you can see that prefetching can be better than increasing your cache size by 8X.
Let's see.
Which makes sense.
I mean, we've seen it with compression also, right?
Compression is a bit harder, but prefetching actually buys you a whole lot.
And the reason is a lot of the cache space that you have is.
Reactive, that's first.
And also you don't have a lot of reuse, right?
There have been a lot of studies that have shown that more than 80% of the data that you have in
your caches are useless.
If you look at the cache at this point in time, more than 80% of the data is not going to be used
anytime into the future, right?
It's good to know that.
So our caches are extremely inefficient, but they do improve performance.
If you keep adding caches, this doesn't mean that they're efficient in improving performance, right?
So there are other techniques like prefetching or compression that can improve performance with much
better efficiency, right?
OK, So there are many prefetching issues, some of which we're going to cover.
We've covered some of these over here.
There are also other issues like throttling of the prefetchers because if you have multiple
prefetchers, how do you manage the prefetchers and swaddling?
Essentially all thrusters do some sort of throttling today based on feedback that they get in terms
of how good the prefetchers are.
You want to throttle inaccurate prefetchers, you want to throttle down inaccurate prefetchers and
throttle up accurate prefetches.
They also cause more issues in multi core multipressers, the multipresser multi threaded systems.
This is 1 paper that we wrote I guess a lot of time ago these days.
This actually has a nice description of the prefetcher that is employed in Intel Pentium 4 at the
time, which is a locality based prefetcher.
It's streaming, but it's more locality patterns if it's kind of guesses which side of the where the
processor is going and it has a window of what to prefetch and it keeps moving that window in a
sliding manner as it gets hints as to whether the processor is actually using the prefetches in the
window.
So it's actually a very interesting prefetcher design, which is more complicated than streaming
prefetchers and also striding prefetchers that we're going to talk about.
But this is an example of throttling the prefetchers.
So stream prefetcher, have you already seen, I already talked about this, I'm not going to talk
about it, but let's talk about strike prefetcher.
You may have guessed the idea.
Stride is basically, you've seen the strides in vector processing, right?
Stride is the distance between the elements that you're accessing in memory.
Here we're talking about cache blocks, not necessarily word distance.
And here you can see a pattern with stride N, and it's very easy to detect.
The idea is to record the stride between consecutive memory accesses.
If the stride is stable, use it to predict next M memory accesses, right?
What does it mean for the stride to be stable?
You see the same stride multiple times, so you add a confidence counter saying I've seen the same
strides more than three times without it changing, right?
That's the idea.
So there are two types of these stride prefetchers.
You can determine the stride on a per instruction basis, meaning per program counter basis.
This captures a stride for that program counter.
Or you can determine it on a per memory region basis.
This captures stride that may happen due to multiple program counters, multiple instructions, and
both of them happen in real programs.
So this is 1 hardware designed for an instruction based stride prefetcher.
You have a program counter.
You index a table.
The table is tagged with the program counter as bits, and it's also stores the last address
referenced by the program counter.
These are cache block addresses and the last stride seen and the confidence in the stride.
How many times the last stride was seen as a saturating counter?
Right now, each load store instruction can lead to a memory access pattern with the different
strides, and this structure can detect strides caused by each instruction.
It could be a very small table.
Actually.
Timeless of prefetches can be an issue over here because when you fetch the load and you index into
the pit table, when you actually get the program counter of the load, initiating the prefetch
during that time may be too late because the load is going to miss from memory, for example.
And you basically initiate the prefetch when the load is fetched, the load is going to execute 10
cycles later, right?
So you're going to say 10 cycles out of 500 cycles.
Not so good.
So a lot of the designs take into account the timeless.
So they try to do this much earlier than when the load is fetched.
So a potential solution is look ahead in the instruction stream.
So if you're running again your fetch engine faster than your back end, so you keep generating
branch predictions, you keep fetching instructions, putting them in a queue and the back end is
consuming them whenever it can consume them.
The front end of the processor can run faster and as a result you can do this pre fetching also
earlier.
Basically the front end is looking ahead much further than the back end is, right?
That's the idea.
So that's one way of looking ahead.
Another way of looking ahead is of course prefetching essentially 10 next accesses, right as opposed
to just one next access.
And that's possible also to do OK memory region based strike prefetching is based based.
I need to fix that and memory region based strike prefetching is actually simpler in terms of the
tables that you need to do you index.
With a cache block address and you chop it.
Basically this gives you the region and you there's A tag and there's a stride associated with that
region and you need to basically generate the next address based on that stride.
So this can detect strided memory access patterns that appear due to multiple instructions.
Each access over here could be due to a different instruction, for example.
That could happen in real programs and they do happen.
And stream prefetching stream buffers is a special case of memory region based stride prefetching
where N is 1 essentially, right?
OK, so that's very interesting.
So instruction based stride prefetching, this is 1 paper that is interesting.
A lot of these concepts were developed in 1980s actually IBM 36091 from 1960s had an instruction
based, instruction based prefetcher, stream prefetcher, not strike prefetcher.
So these have been around for a while and they've been employed in real processors if you're
interested in looking at it.
And memory region based stream prefetching was from this paper that we discussed.
OK, those are simple access patterns.
What about more complex access patterns?
So if it's simple regular strike, prefetchers do well.
If you have complex regular patterns, multiple regular strides, you just need to detect them, and
existing processors are very good at that.
I'm going to give you one example of this delta correlation prefetchers.
Then there are irregular patterns where you cannot have this sort of delta correlations.
How do you prefetch them?
Linked data structures, indirect array accesses, random accesses.
They're actually very difficult to prefetch access patterns, but people have developed mechanisms to
prefetch for them.
OK, let's take a look at one of these.
This is workload, and this is the delta pattern that you have.
Miss pattern.
What is the delta between different miss accesses, right?
You can see that something is repeating over here, right?
And if you can record that nicely, you can do that.
So this is one example that was written by folks at Texas A&M and Intel that is employed, well, a
version of this is employed in a lot of systems today.
The key idea is given a history or pattern or signature of stride, record and predict what stride
might come next, right?
There's one way of implementing it.
There are multiple ways of implementation, of course.
So for example, if you see 7 -, 612 in sequence, that may predict 6.
If you see -612 six in sequence, that predicts -5 right.
I'm not going to the detail, but you need, you may need to actually have a confidence threshold.
Basically, you're keeping track of a path.
And if that path confidence perhaps below a threshold, you don't predict.
So you do history of strides, you do a prediction and keep track of a confidence for that prediction
as well as the path that you followed.
And that confidence over time drops.
And at some point you're really not confident and you stop prefetching.
So this is one example, again, without going into a lot of implementation conceptual example, many
questions, we're going to go into more sophisticated topics and I have time to cover a machine
learning based prefetcher.
OK, cool.
There are many, many prefetchers that I can talk about and there are many, many cool ideas actually
in this area.
I think creativity is our limiter over here.
One example idea that I really like is content directed prefetching.
We worked on this idea.
It was originally allowed by Intel, Bob Cooksey, Stefan Jordan, etcetera in 1998.
And the idea is whenever the processor acts as a cache block, scan that cache block and if anything
looks like a pointer, generate a prefetch for it.
Then the question is, what does look like a pointer?
Of course, if you do this wildly, meaning without confidence, you prefetch a lot.
So we develop mechanisms to make this, make this more confident, meaning don't prefetch for all the
pointers, prefetch for pointers that you think are going to be used.
So if you think about this prefetchers, it's called content directed prefetcher and Apple actually
has an implementation of it.
This is very public and people have actually attacked that.
Good ideas.
I could implement it.
The basic thing is this is a stateless prefetcher.
You have the cache block, you just need to scan it to find addresses, right?
And you just need to predict which addresses may be actually useful for you in the future.
You don't need to keep any state.
The state is in your cache.
So this sort of idea is very nice, I think, in terms of creativity.
OK, I'm going to give you another idea.
And also it gets implemented, as you can see, with some optimizations.
In the end, this is a paper that we wrote again with Rahul, and the idea is here is to design A
prefetcher that uses reinforcement learning principles.
I'll give you the idea relatively quickly.
Reinforcement learning is essentially a method of machine learning.
It's an algorithmic approach to take an action in a given situation to maximise a numerical reward,
right?
You have an agent, you have an environment, and agent observes a state and takes an action and
eventually gets a reward and it's learns to associate.
States with actions that would maximise the long term reward.
We are all reinforcement learning agents.
Humans are reinforcement learning agents, right?
We interact with our environment, we take actions and we get rewards or punishments.
And based on that we essentially determine our next action given the same state or same type of
state let's say.
So agent stores Q values for every state.
Action pair quality values and this actually denotes the expected return for taking an action in a
state.
And the idea is to give an estate select an action that provides the highest Q value and Q values
are determined based on some future look like.
You don't want to actually maximise the reward for just one action.
You want to maximise overall reward that you're going to get during the time of execution.
And there are methods for doing that.
So essentially here we formulate prefetching as a reinforcement learning problem.
Agents as a prefetcher environment is the processor and the system prefetcher observes a feature of
a memory request to address a the program counter.
For example, it could be deltas that you observed recently.
It could be anything.
Basically, you could do a feature selection in the end and it decides to prefetch from address A+
offset, It predicts offset O.
This is a particular type of prefetching mechanism.
You can actually generalise it to more, and I hope people generalise it because there's more to do
in this area.
And then it gets a reward whether the prefetch is used or not, for example, or when it's used,
etcetera.
And then it basically updates the Q values for the given state and the action pair.
OK, So state is essentially in this case AK dimensional vector of features.
It could be control flow and data flow features.
For example, the program counter of the load branch, program counter, last three program counters,
control flow path that you've taken, etcetera.
There could be many things here, data flow example, it could be the cache line address you're
touching, physical page number, delta between the last few cache addresses, etcetera.
So in the end, you need to do some feature selection to reduce the state space because if you
actually include all of them and you need to do a table look up, that's pretty expensive, right?
You want to actually reduce it as much as possible so that it's implementable within a frequency
target.
Action is essentially in this case, it depends on the algorithm, type of algorithm that you want to
implement.
And we basically have selecting A prefetch offset O as the action given an access to address a
action space is limited in this case, assuming you're operating within a page boundary that we will
talk a lot about next week.
And 0 offset means no prefetch is generated.
And you can also prune the action space by doing some design space exploration.
Rewards is important to define.
This defines the objective of this sort of prefetcher.
And you can encapsulate a lot of things over here, the prefetch usefulness, for example, system
level feedback, whether the memory bandwidth is being used, whether you're getting cache pollution,
whether you're consuming more energy, etcetera.
And in this paper, we look at memory bandwidth use, just feedback, for example.
So reward functions are also really important and this is the configuration that we examine.
You can derive a lot of these using automatic design space exploration.
So it's a very simple version of the concept.
Only two features, 16 prefetch offsets and these are the rewards that you get.
If the prefetch is accurate and timely, you get a positive, high positive reward.
If the prefetch is inaccurate and you have high memory bandwidth usage, at that point in time,
you've done something really bad.
You get a high negative reward.
If the prefetch is not used, for example, you get a zero reward or something.
And the good news is you can configure the prefetcher for different targets by changing their reward
values.
So this actually, as we have shown in this work, it's dynamically customisable.
You don't need to change your hardware, but you can dynamically program your prefetcher to become
better.
And I think there's more opportunity for that also.
So there's more detailed things that are overviewed in the paper that I'm not going to talk about.
This is a table look up based reinforcement learning mechanism.
So whenever you get a demand request, you extract the state and you basically hash the state and you
index into a table that essentially gives you the Q values for each action that you may want to
implement.
And for the actions with the highest Q values, like let's say offset 5 has the highest Q value,
generate a prefetch.
You can of course generate multiple actions also, right?
Highest Q values for three actions, for example.
And then you have an evaluation queue that keeps track of whether your actions were useful and
timely.
And based on that, you update the quality values for the actions you've taken for a given state,
right?
That's how it works, basically reinforcement learning.
It's implementable in hardware.
As you can see, it's actually very hardware friendly.
You could also do deep reinforcement learning, which we didn't do in this case.
In deep reinforcement learning, that table is kind of replaced with a neural network.
You can do both hybrid also.
Actually, you may have a deep neural network over there, but we don't want to have really expensive
multiplications.
Because they actually are energy consuming plus long latency.
But in other works we have deep reinforcement learning mechanisms.
OK, in the end, if you do this, you get good performance.
That's the take away.
And you can do this in simulation, basically.
Of course, we do this in simulation because it's very hard to design these things in real hardware,
but possible these days more easily.
So your performance increases with core counts.
It's actually very good at low DM bandwidth because you're very selective of the accuracy is very
high.
And it's all open source.
So you can also improve it.
By the way, we organised, Rahul and I organised a championship data prefetching championship this
year at HPCA conference.
Essentially all prefetchers use this as a baseline.
So this, this took off really nicely.
And it's, it's really a common baseline for all prefetchers that people develop going into the
future.
So I can learn more about Pithia and the PDF paper is this.
If you want to learn more about reinforcement learning, this is a beautiful book by Rich Sutton and
Andrew Barto.
They finally won the Turing Award and I believe they deserved it much earlier.
But for some reason, reinforcement learning was not hot for many years, even though it's been around
for a long time.
But this is a really great book.
And they have also applications and case studies.
We've been working on reinforcement learning for a while and these folks found our memory controller
based mechanisms, reinforcement learning based memory controllers worthy of including in their
paper also so in their in their book.
So there are a bunch of things over here that are quite interesting.
OK, I think this is a good place to stop.
Next week we're going to pick up with more hardware prefetchers and we're going to talk about the
one of the most hairiest part of system design, which is virtual memory.
And then we're going to conclude.
Sounds good.
OK, have a nice weekend.
Hopefully I'll see you next week also.